that this crisis was an opportunity for Greece, for Europe, for the world, to make radical democratic transformations in our institutions. Instead, I had a very humbling experience. In Brussels, when we tried desperately again and again to find common solutions, I realized that not one, not one of us, had ever dealt with a similar crisis. But worse, we were trapped by our collective ignorance. We were led by our fears. And our fears led to a blind faith in the orthodoxy of austerity. Instead of reaching out to the common or the collective wisdom in our societies, investing in it to find more creative solutions, we reverted to political posturing. And then we were surprised when every ad hoc new measure didn't bring an end to the crisis, and of course that made it very easy to look for a whipping boy for our collective European failure, and of course that was Greece. Those profligate, idle, ouzo-swilling, Zorba-dancing Greeks, they are the problem. Punish them! Well, a convenient but unfounded stereotype that sometimes hurt even more than austerity itself. But let me warn you, this is not just about Greece. This could be the pattern that leaders follow again and again when we deal with these complex, cross-border problems, whether it's climate change, whether it's migration, whether it's the financial system. That is, abandoning our collective power to imagine our potential, falling victims to our fears, our stereotypes, our dogmas, taking our citizens out of the process rather than building the process around our citizens. And doing so will only test the faith of our citizens, of our peoples, even more in the democratic process. It's no wonder that many political leaders, and I don't exclude myself, have lost the trust of our people. When riot police have to protect parliaments, a scene which is increasingly common around the world, then there's something deeply wrong with our democracies. That's why I called for a referendum to have the Greek people own and decide on the terms of the rescue package. My European counterparts, some of them, at least, said, "You can't do this. There will be havoc in the markets again." I said, "We need to, before we restore confidence in the markets, we need to restore confidence and trust amongst our people." Since leaving office, I have had time to reflect. We have weathered the storm, in Greece and in Europe, but we remain challenged. If politics is the power to imagine and use our potential, well then 60-percent youth unemployment in Greece, and in other countries, certainly is a lack of imagination if not a lack of compassion. So far, we've thrown economics at the problem, actually mostly austerity, and certainly we could have designed alternatives, a different strategy, a green stimulus for green jobs, or mutualized debt, Eurobonds which would support countries in need from market pressures, these would have been much more viable alternatives. Yet I have come to believe that the problem is not so much one of economics as it is one of democracy. So let's try something else. Let's see how we can bring people back to the process. Let's throw democracy at the problem. Again, the Ancient Greeks, with all their shortcomings, believed in the wisdom of the crowd at their best moments. In people we trust. Democracy could not work without the citizens deliberating, debating, taking on public responsibilities for public affairs. Average citizens often were chosen for citizen juries to decide on critical matters of the day. Science, theater, research, philosophy, games of the mind and the body, they were daily exercises. Actually they were an education for participation, for the potential, for growing the potential of our citizens. And those who shunned politics, well, they were idiots. You see, in Ancient Greece, in ancient Athens, that term originated there. "Idiot" comes from the root "idio," oneself. A person who is self-centered, secluded, excluded, someone who doesn't participate or even examine public affairs. And participation took place in the agora, the agora having two meanings, both a marketplace and a place where there was political deliberation. You see, markets and politics then were one, unified, accessible, transparent, because they gave power to the people. They serve the demos, democracy. Above government, above markets was the direct rule of the people. Today we have globalized the markets but we have not globalized our democratic institutions. So our politicians are limited to local politics, while our citizens, even though they see a great potential, are prey to forces beyond their control. So how then do we reunite the two halves of the agora? How do we democratize globalization? And I'm not talking about the necessary reforms of the United Nations or the G20. I'm talking about, how do we secure the space, the demos, the platform of values, so that we can tap into all of your potential? Well, this is exactly where I think Europe fits in. Europe, despite its recent failures, is the world's most successful cross-border peace experiment. So let's see if it can't be an experiment in global democracy, a new kind of democracy. Let's see if we can't design a European agora, not simply for products and services, but for our citizens, where they can work together, deliberate, learn from each other, exchange between art and cultures, where they can come up with creative solutions. Let's imagine that European citizens actually have the power to vote directly for a European president, or citizen juries chosen by lottery which can deliberate on critical and controversial issues, a European-wide referendum where our citizens, as the lawmakers, vote on future treaties. And here's an idea: Why not have the first truly European citizens by giving our immigrants, not Greek or German or Swedish citizenship, but a European citizenship? And make sure we actually empower the unemployed by giving them a voucher scholarship where they can choose to study anywhere in Europe. Where our common identity is democracy, where our education is through participation, and where participation builds trust and solidarity rather than exclusion and xenophobia. Europe of and by the people, a Europe, an experiment in deepening and widening democracy beyond borders. Now, some might accuse me of being naive, putting my faith in the power and the wisdom of the people. Well, after decades in politics, I am also a pragmatist. Believe me, I have been, I am, part of today's political system, and I know things must change. We must revive politics as the power to imagine, reimagine, and redesign for a better world. But I also know that this disruptive force of change won't be driven by the politics of today. The revival of democratic politics will come from you, and I mean all of you. Everyone who participates in this global exchange of ideas, whether it's here in this room or just outside this room or online or locally, where everybody lives, everyone who stands up to injustice and inequality, everybody who stands up to those who preach racism rather than empathy, dogma rather than critical thinking, technocracy rather than democracy, everyone who stands up to the unchecked power, whether it's authoritarian leaders, plutocrats hiding their assets in tax havens, or powerful lobbies protecting the powerful few. It is in their interest that all of us are idiots. Let's not be. Thank you. (Applause) Bruno Giussani: You seem to describe a political leadership that is kind of unprepared and a prisoner of the whims of the financial markets, and that scene in Brussels that you describe, to me, as a citizen, is terrifying. Help us understand how you felt after the decision. It was not a good decision, clearly, but how do you feel after that, not as the prime minister, but as George? George Papandreou: Well, obviously there were constraints which didn't allow me or others to make the types of decisions we would have wanted, and obviously I had hoped that we would have the time to make the reforms which would have dealt with the deficit rather than trying to cut the deficit which was the symptom of the problem. And that hurt. That hurt because that, first of all, hurt the younger generation, and not only, many of them are demonstrating outside, but I think this is one of our problems. When we face these crises, we have kept the potential, the huge potential of our society out of this process, and we are closing in on ourselves in politics, and I think we need to change that, to really find new participatory ways using the great capabilities that now exist even in technology but not only in technology, the minds that we have, and I think we can find solutions which are much better, but we have to be open. BG: You seem to suggest that the way forward is more Europe, and that is not to be an easy discourse right now in most European countries. It's rather the other way -- more closed borders and less cooperation and maybe even stepping out of some of the different parts of the European construction. How do you reconcile that? GP: Well, I think one of the worst things that happened during this crisis is that we started a blame game. And the fundamental idea of Europe is that we can cooperate beyond borders, go beyond our conflicts and work together. And the paradox is that, because we have this blame game, we have less the potential to convince our citizens that we should work together, while now is the time when we really need to bring our powers together. Now, more Europe for me is not simply giving more power to Brussels. It is actually giving more power to the citizens of Europe, that is, really making Europe a project of the people. So that, I think, would be a way to answer some of the fears that we have in our society. BG: George, thank you for coming to TED. GP: Thank you very much.BG: Thank you.(Applause)
que esta crisis fuera una oportunidad para Grecia, para Europa, para el mundo, para hacer las transformaciones democráticas radicales en nuestras instituciones. En cambio, tuve una lección de humildad. En Bruselas, cuando intentamos desesperadamente una y otra vez encontrar soluciones comunes, me di cuenta de que ninguno, ninguno de nosotros, nunca había tratado con una crisis similar. Pero peor aún, estábamos atrapados en nuestra ignorancia colectiva. Fuimos guiados por nuestros miedos. Y nuestros temores nos condujeron a una fe ciega en la ortodoxia de la austeridad. En lugar de acercarse al común o la a sabiduría colectiva de nuestras sociedades, invirtiendo en ella para encontrar soluciones más creativas, nos devolvimos a la postura política. Y entonces nos sorprendimos cuando cada nueva medida ad hoc no ponía fin a la crisis, y por supuesto esto hace muy fácil buscar a un chivo expiatorio por nuestro fracaso colectivo europeo, y por supuesto ese fue Grecia. Los griegos derrochadores, perezosos, bebedores de ouzo, bailarines de Zorba, ellos son el problema. ¡Castiguémoslos! Bueno, un estereotipo infundado pero conveniente lo que a veces dolió aún más que la austeridad misma. Pero déjeme advertirles, no se trata solo de Grecia. Este podría ser el patrón que los líderes seguimos una y otra vez cuando nos ocupamos de estos problemas complejos, transnacionales, sea el cambio climático, la migración, o el sistema financiero. Es decir, abandonar nuestro poder colectivo de imaginar nuestro potencial, caer víctimas de nuestros miedos, nuestros estereotipos, nuestros dogmas, sacando a nuestros ciudadanos fuera del proceso, en vez de construir el proceso alrededor de nuestros ciudadanos. Y hacerlo, solo probará la fe de nuestros ciudadanos, de nuestros pueblos, aún más, en el proceso democrático. No es de extrañar que muchos líderes políticos, y no me excluyo, hayan perdido la confianza de sus pueblos. Cuando la policía antidisturbios tiene que proteger los parlamentos, una escena que es cada vez más común en el mundo, entonces hay algo profundamente equivocado en nuestras democracias. Por eso hice un llamado a un referéndum para que el pueblo griego se apropiara y decidiera los términos del paquete de rescate. Mis colegas europeos, algunos de ellos, al menos, dijeron: "No puede hacer eso. Habrá caos en los mercados otra vez". Yo dije, "Lo necesitamos, antes que restablecer la confianza de los mercados, tenemos que restablecer la seguridad y la confianza entre nuestros pueblos". Desde que abandoné el cargo, he tenido tiempo para reflexionar. Hemos capeado el temporal, en Grecia y en Europa, pero seguimos siendo desafiados. Si la política es el poder de imaginar y utilizar nuestro potencial, bien, entonces, el 60 % de desempleo juvenil en Grecia, y en otros países, es sin duda una falta de imaginación si no una falta de compasión. Hasta ahora, hemos lanzado economía al problema, realmente sobre todo austeridad, y sin duda podríamos haber diseñado alternativas, una estrategia diferente, un estímulo verde para empleos verdes, o mutualizar la deuda, eurobonos con que apoyar a los países necesitados por las presiones del mercado, estas habrían sido alternativas más viables. Sin embargo he llegado a creer que el problema no es tanto económico como uno de la democracia. Así que intentemos algo más. Vamos a ver cómo podemos traer gente hacia el proceso. Vamos a lanzar democracia al problema. Una vez más, los antiguos griegos, con todos sus defectos, creían en la sabiduría de la multitud en sus mejores momentos. Confiamos en la gente. La democracia no podría funcionar sin los ciudadanos deliberando, debatiendo, asumiendo responsabilidades públicas de asuntos públicos. Los ciudadanos promedio a menudo fueron elegidos como jurados para decidir sobre asuntos críticos del momento. Ciencia, investigación, teatro, filosofía, juegos de la mente y el cuerpo, eran ejercicios diarios. Realmente fueron una educación para la participación, el potencial para crecer, el potencial de nuestros ciudadanos. Y los que rechazaban la política, pues eran idiotas. Verán, en la antigua Grecia, en la antigua Atenas, ese término se originó allí. "Idiota" proviene de la raíz "idio", uno mismo. Una persona que es egocéntrica, aislada, excluida, alguien que no participa o incluso no examina asuntos públicos. Y la participación tuvo lugar en la ágora, la ágora tiene dos significados, un mercado y un lugar donde se produjo la deliberación política. Ven, mercados y política eran entonces uno, unificado, accesible, transparente, porque dieron el poder al pueblo. Sirven al 'demos' [pueblo], democracia. Sobre el gobierno, por encima de los mercados estaba la regla directa del pueblo. Hoy hemos globalizado los mercados pero no hemos globalizado nuestras instituciones democráticas. Así que nuestros políticos se limitan a la política local, mientras los ciudadanos, aunque ven un gran potencial, son presa de fuerzas ajenas a su voluntad. Así que, ¿cómo reunificamos las dos mitades de la ágora? ¿Cómo democratizamos la globalización? Y no estoy hablando de las reformas necesarias de las Naciones Unidas o el G-20. Estoy hablando, de cómo aseguramos el espacio, el pueblo, la plataforma de valores, por los que podemos aprovechar todo su potencial. Bueno, esto es exactamente donde creo que Europa encaja. Europa, a pesar de sus fracasos recientes, es el experimento de paz transfronteriza más exitoso del mundo. Así que veamos si no puede ser un experimento en la democracia global, un nuevo tipo de democracia. Vamos a ver si no podemos diseñar una ágora europea, no solo para los productos y servicios, sino para nuestros ciudadanos, donde puedan trabajar juntos, deliberar, aprender unos de otros, intercambiar entre arte y culturas, donde se puede topar con soluciones creativas. Imaginemos que los ciudadanos europeos realmente tienen el poder de votar directamente por un presidente europeo, o ser jurados ciudadanos elegidos por sorteo que puedan deliberar sobre cuestiones críticas y polémicas, un referéndum pan-europeo donde nuestros ciudadanos, como los legisladores voten en futuros tratados. Y aquí está una idea: ¿Por qué no tenemos los primeros ciudadanos verdaderamente europeos dando a nuestros inmigrantes, ciudadanía no griega o alemana o sueca, sino una ciudadanía europea? Y asegurándonos de que realmente potenciamos los desempleados dándoles una beca para poder estudiar en cualquier lugar de Europa. Donde nuestra identidad común es la democracia, dónde nuestra educación es a través de la participación, y donde la participación genera confianza y solidaridad en lugar de exclusión y xenofobia. Europa de y para la gente, una Europa, un experimento en la profundización y ampliación democrática más allá de las fronteras. Ahora, algunos podrían acusarme de ser ingenuo, al poner mi fe en el poder y la sabiduría del pueblo. Bueno, después de décadas en la política, yo también soy un pragmático. Créanme, he sido, soy parte del sistema político actual, y sé que las cosas deben cambiar. Debemos revivir la política como el poder de imaginar, reimaginar y rediseñar un mundo mejor. Pero también sé que esta disruptiva fuerza de cambio no debe ser conducida por la política de hoy. El renacimiento de la política democrática vendrá de Uds. y me refiero a todos Uds. Todo aquel que participa en este intercambio global de ideas, sea aquí en esta sala o fuera de esta sala o en línea o localmente, donde cada uno vive, todo aquel que se levanta ante la injusticia y la desigualdad, todo el que se levanta ante los predicadores del racismo en lugar de la empatía, del dogma en lugar del pensamiento crítico, de la tecnocracia, en lugar de la democracia, todos los que se enfrentan al poder sin control, sea de líderes autoritarios, plutócratas ocultando sus activos en paraísos fiscales, o aquellos poderosos que cabildean protegiendo a unos pocos con poder. Es de su interés que todos nosotros seamos idiotas. No lo seamos. Gracias. (Aplausos) Bruno Giussani: Parece describir un liderazgo político que no está preparado y es preso de los caprichos de los mercados financieros, y esa escena en Bruselas que Ud. describe, para mí, como ciudadano, es terrible. Ayúdenos a entender cómo se sentía después de la decisión. Claramente no fue una buena decisión, pero, ¿cómo se siente después de eso, no como primer ministro, sino como George? George Papandreou: Bueno, obviamente había limitaciones que no me permitían a mí o a otros tomar los tipos de decisiones que hubiésemos querido, y obviamente esperaba que haber tenido el tiempo para hacer las reformas que se habrían ocupado del déficit, en lugar de intentar reducir el déficit que era el síntoma del problema. Y eso dolió. Eso dolió porque, ante todo, lastima a la generación más joven y no solo, muchos de ellos se están manifestando afuera, pero creo que este es uno de nuestros problemas. Cuando enfrentamos estas crisis, hemos mantenido el potencial, el enorme potencial de nuestra sociedad, fuera de este proceso, y nos estamos encerrando nosotros mismos en la política, y creo que tenemos que cambiar esto, realmente encontrar nuevas formas de participación mediante las grandes capacidades que ahora existen incluso en tecnología pero no solo en tecnología, las mentes que tenemos, y creo que podemos encontrar soluciones que son mucho mejores, pero tenemos que estar abiertos. BG: Parece sugerir que el camino a seguir es más Europa, y no debe ser un discurso fácil ahora en la mayoría de los países europeos. Es más bien lo contrario, más fronteras cerradas y menos cooperación y tal vez incluso separarse de algunas de las diferentes partes de la construcción europea. ¿Cómo conciliar esto? GP: Bien, creo que una de las peores cosas que sucedieron durante esta crisis es que comenzamos un juego de culpa. Y la idea fundamental de Europa es que podemos cooperar más allá de las fronteras, más allá de nuestros conflictos y trabajar juntos. Y la paradoja es que, dado que tenemos este juego de culpa, tenemos menos potencial para convencer a los ciudadanos de que debemos trabajar juntos, mientras que ahora es el momento en que realmente necesitamos reunir nuestros poderes. Ahora, más Europa para mí no es simplemente darle más poder a Bruselas. Es realmente darles más poder a los ciudadanos de Europa, es decir, realmente hacer de Europa un proyecto de la gente. Por lo que, creo, sería una forma de responder a algunos de los temores que tenemos en nuestra sociedad. BG: George, gracias por venir a TED. GP: Muchas gracias. BG: Gracias. (Aplausos)